Happy Diwali! So Diwali is coming, and there's
a lot of excitement around Diwali.
Every year, there are many different kinds of festivals. It's a
very joyous festival.
So, there are many things
you shouldn't give up on this festival. You clean your house,
you invite Goddess Lakshmi into your home.
People
celebrate in different ways. Today,
we'll talk about financial
habits that you can give up, that
you can step out of your house
and clean your house. Diwali and
finance have a very direct relationship, so
we can talk about financial habits.
Here, what are those financial
habits that don't allow you to
grow financially, that do
n't allow your wealth to grow? So,
we'll talk about them today. Before we start the video,
I'd like to wish
you and your family a
very happy Diwali. From our family to yours,
and I wish that every
kind of happiness comes to your home this Diwali. The
first financial habit we need to break, that
we need to get rid of, is
holding.  Bad Financial Products
What do we do in our house during Diwali? We
clean the house. There is some old stuff in the house
which is not needed or has been lying there for a long time
and we know that we have to
clean it because we have to welcome Goddess Lakshmi,
so we go out of the house in the
same way. You
buy bad financial products, so
you buy it, a relative told
you to buy it, your insurance agent
told you to buy it, but that product is
not in sync with your financial goals.
Your financial goal says something else but
that product says something else, it is
not helping you in achieving your targets,
but it is definitely helping the person who sent you the product
in achieving his targets.
What happens is that generally we buy the
products, we do not open them and see, we
buy them and then many times we do
not even continue. Many times the
products are not in sync with us, they are
high cost products. So this Diwali, while
you are sitting at home, open your financial
documents file,
open your policies and check which are those
products which are not in sync with you,
which are not in sync with your gold.
Those who are not in line with your risk appetite,
sell them to them and
get the exact amount from them, so you should sell the debt to
them and get the exact amount from them, so you should have
a clear and clutter free financial life,
along with that, arrange all your financial
documents and
reduce clutter, this is what we do on Diwali, we
eliminate clutter,
we organize all those things and
keep them properly, similarly keep your financial
documents well, so that the debt
remains with you in the future and you can
withdraw it easily, stop thinking about the next credit card as a free
money.  Many times we
feel that our credit card is
free money. It is not so. Credit card is a
convenience. Credit card is not a loan.
You are the credit card company. Do not take a loan.
You should consider it convenient that you have less
interest and flexibility. Why am I saying this
because credit card users are
increasing and
for small transactions, even if it is a transaction of Rs 200-300,
we swipe the credit card
and many people have a
loan running under the credit card as well. That means the
bill of the credit card is more than the actual pay capacity.
So what are they doing in it?
They pay the minimum amount due to which
they have to pay up to 50-55% interest. That
means interest charges of 3 to 4-5% are levied every
month due to which they fall
into a dead trap. Consider your
credit card as convenience only. Do
not consider it as free money.
When you leave this habit, you will automatically
see that  Now gradually if you are
stuck in credit card debt then you will come out of it.
Next habit is to stop
procrastinating. It happens a lot, meaning you
should delay. It happens a lot. We delete a lot of
things. For example, if
we have to go to the dentist, we will
not go unless there is a lot of pain
or you know, there is unbearable pain,
we are not able to tolerate it at all, then
we will go to the dentist. Similarly,
in finance also we procrastinate a lot of things. For example, if
we have to
start an SIP, we will not do it, we will do it
next year, we will wait for some
income tax benefit next year or we will think,
analyze and then do it.
Secondly, if we want to buy an insurance policy,
we will keep procrastinating, we will keep taking decisions,
we will keep researching but
we will not take it. Similar terminology is the same in this also,
we will keep researching, we will
not take it for any reason,
we will make any excuse but we will not take it because
deleting is human nature. For
example, if you have to visit the bank, for a long
time you have been saying that  You have to
visit the bank, you have to check the nominations in the bank,
who are the nominations in the FDS, whether there are
proper nominations or not, but you should
take decisions and keep them in your mind,
you also have this thought that I have to reduce this,
remove that and get
rid of it quickly. Another financial habit that we have to
break is that we do not make a budget, we
know verbally that we have spent so much at home,
our income is so much, these are our
expenses, we
went out to dinner, spent so much, ate so much on petrol,
but we never document it, we do not
make a budget at one place.
What is a budget? A budget is just about writing down your expenses,
that you have spent this much, this is your
source of income and this is your surplus savings,
so you should have a clear
picture of what your expenses are,
what your needs are and what your wants are, it is
very important to make a budget. I have
seen my parents in my house, while making a budget, at the
beginning of the month itself they allocate
these fees.  This is the amount of money, this is the
amount for utility bills, this is the amount for the kitchen, it used to be given
to mom and at the end of the
month I have seen dad writing
that this was spent and this is what I have
left. This knowledge of savings is a very simple process, I mean there are very old techniques too, you can make it on Excel, you can make it on a notebook, there are many applications also, you can make it on that, so budget is such a habit, sir,
which will help you in taking your financial life to the
next level, the next is
planning for important things, we
plan for everything in our life, for example, if we want to buy a
mobile phone, then the whole
family will sit and plan which phone to buy, they will do
complete research, how many pixels,
camera, how many GB storage,
we will compare many features on hand,
but when we have to plan for our gold,
for financial gold, which is
our priority due to which we are
able to make all these efforts, then we have to plan for that,
for example, we have to
plan for our retirement, date is the
most  One note, goal planning will come when you are about to
retire, then we will see, if
this does not happen then whatever
important gold you have in your life, make it a
priority, make a habit of proper
planning, when we go on vacation, we do a
lot of planning, where to go,
which place to go, which hotel to
stay in, which flights to take and so on,
here also planning of your gold is
very important, only when you
plan, you will be able to allocate for it, only
then that goal will be accomplished, so
we say that dream,
but also make efforts to fulfill your dreams, so
dreams become reality, one intention becomes
action, so you have to show that action,
you have to do that planning, so that your
dreams can become reality, so
these are the five financial habits from my side, when
you get rid of them, if you get them out of your house,
then automatically your financial
life will move to the next level and this
Diwali try to get rid of these financial habits
and these financial habits,
you and your  All the family
members were also there, from my side I would like to
wish you again in today's video
a very Happy Diwali and Safe
Diwali, take care of yourself, we will meet
you soon with another new informative video,
stay safe take care, bye bye